Guide to the Orpheus M. McAdoo and Mattie Allen McAdoo Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Orpheus M. McAdoo and Mattie Allen McAdoo papers
1850-1966
1886-1936
JWJ MSS 60
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.88
(10 boxes)
The collection consists of material documenting the entrepreneurial and performance activities of Orpheus M. McAdoo as a member of the Jubilee Singers and director of the Virginia Concert Company and Jubilee Singers, as well as material relating to Mattie Allen McAdoo and the McAdoo and Allen families. Highlights include scrapbooks containing announcements, clippings, and ephemera for the Fisk Jubilee Singers Tour of Australia in 1886-1888 and "McAdoo's Virginia Jubilee Singers and Concert Company, Clippings from Papers throughout Australasia" in 1893-1895; photographs of Orpheus McAdoo, Mattie Allen McAdoo, and one or more of McAdoo's troupes (possibly the Virginia Jubilee Singers and/or the Georgia Minstrels and Alabama Cakewalkers); and artifacts, such as beads, beaded jewelry, a spearhead and pipe, presumably collected by the McAdoos while on tour in South Africa. Also found are the license and invitation for the marriage of Orpheus and Mattie McAdoo and the certificate and announcement for the birth of their son, Myron; sheet music for songs perhaps performed by Orpheus McAdoo and Mattie Allen McAdoo; numerous family photographs (many of which are unidentified); personal and financial papers of Mattie Allen McAdoo; and material relating to various members of the McAdoo and Allen families, including Myron McAdoo, Myra McAdoo, and Lula Allen.
McAdoo, Orpheus M. (Orpheus Myron), 1858-1900
McAdoo, Mattie Allen
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from the William Reese Company on the James Weldon Johnson Memorial Collection of Negro Arts & Letters Fund, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Orpheus M. McAdoo and Mattie Allen McAdoo
Biographical information is drawn from Lynn Abbott and Doug Seroff, Out of Sight: The Rise of African American Popular Music, 1889-1895 (Jackson: University Press of Mississippi, 2002), pp. 119-140.
Orpheus M. McAdoo (1858-1900)
Orpheus McAdoo was born in Greensboro, North Carolina on January 4, 1858. He graduated from Hampton Institute in 1876, and taught school in rural Virginia for three years and then at the Hampton preparatory school for several years. In 1885, McAdoo joined Frederick Loudin's Jubilee Singers, also known as the Original Fisk Jubilee Singers, and toured with the group in London and Australia. He returned to the United States in 1889 to form his own group, the Virginia Concert Company and Jubilee Singers. Among the people he recruited were Belle F. Gibbons, his younger brother Eugene McAdoo, Madame J. Stewart Ball, his future wife Mattie E. Allen, and Moses Hamilton Hodges. Beginning in 1890, the company toured the British Isles before traveling to South Africa, where they had a great deal of success, performing in large cities as well as more remote regions of the country from 1890 to 1892. In 1892, the company embarked on a tour of Australia and New Zealand. They returned to South Africa in 1895 for a second extended tour, at which point McAdoo transformed the group from the Virginia Concert Company and Jubilee Singers to McAdoo's Minstrel and Vaudeville Company and broadened the list of performers to include variety artists in addition to singers. McAdoo's company headed back to Australia in 1898. While the company toured Australia, McAdoo returned to the United States in 1899 to assemble a full-scale modern African American minstrel troupe, which he named the Georgia Minstrels and Alabama Cakewalkers. The newly-formed company toured Australia from 1899 to 1900. Six weeks after the end of the tour, on July 17, 1900, McAdoo died and was buried in Waverly Cemetery, Sydney.
Mattie Allen McAdoo (1868?-1936)
Mattie Allen McAdoo was born in Columbus, Ohio, circa 1868. After graduating from high school, she taught school, before joining Orpheus McAdoo's Virginia Concert Company and Jubilee Singers as a contralto soloist. She married McAdoo in 1891, and gave birth to a son, Myron, in 1893. After her husband's death in 1900, Mattie McAdoo returned to the United States with her son. She performed as a singer with her sister, Lula Allen, and her brother, Robert Allen. Later in life, she worked for the Phyllis Wheatley YMCA in Washington, D.C. Mattie McAdoo died in 1936.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of material documenting the entrepreneurial and performing activities of Orpheus M. McAdoo as a member of the Jubilee Singers and director of the Virginia Concert Company and Jubilee Singers, as well as material relating to Mattie Allen McAdoo and the McAdoo and Allen families. Highlights include scrapbooks containing announcements, clippings, and ephemera for the Fisk Jubilee Singers Tour of Australia in 1886-1888 and "McAdoo's Virginia Jubilee Singers and Concert Company, Clippings from Papers throughout Australasia" in 1893-1895; photographs of Orpheus McAdoo, Mattie Allen McAdoo, and one or more of McAdoo's troupes (possibly the Virginia Jubilee Singers and/or the Georgia Minstrels and Alabama Cakewalkers); and artifacts, such as beads, beaded jewelry, a spearhead and pipe, presumably collected by the McAdoos while on tour in South Africa. Also found are the license and invitation for the marriage of Orpheus and Mattie McAdoo and the certificate and announcement for the birth of their son, Myron; sheet music for songs perhaps performed by Orpheus McAdoo and Mattie Allen McAdoo; numerous family photographs (many of which are unidentified); personal and financial papers of Mattie Allen McAdoo; and material relating to various members of the McAdoo and Allen families, including Myron McAdoo, Myra McAdoo, and Lula Allen.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Photographs, circa 1860-1960. II. Scrapbooks, 1886-1895. III. Personal and Family Papers, circa 1850-1966. IV. Artifacts, circa 1895.
African Americans -- Music -- 19th century; African American singers -- 19th century; Minstrel shows; Songs; Vaudeville; Australia -- Description and travel; South Africa -- Description and travel; Artifacts (object genre); Photographs; Allen, Lula; McAdoo, Mattie Allen; McAdoo, Myra; McAdoo, Myron; McAdoo, Orpheus M. (Orpheus Myron), 1858-1900; Jubilee Singers; Virginia Concert Company and Jubilee Singers
- Photographs, circa 1860-1960; Series I
  Arrangement
  Arranged by type or subject of photograph.
  - Portraits of Orpheus McAdoo, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Portrait of Orpheus McAdoo, painted photograph in plastic with original frame, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Portraits of Orpheus and Mattie McAdoo and family, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Portraits of Mattie McAdoo (with others), circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Portraits of Myron McAdoo as toddler, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Portrait of Myron McAdoo (?) as young man, circa 1910 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Group portraits of Jubilee Singers, Georgia Minstrels or Alabama Cake Walkers (?), circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cabinet photograph of Orpheus McAdoo's gravestone in Sydney, circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Unidentified family portraits (?), cased photographs: 3 tintypes (2 without cases), circa 1865 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Unidentified family portrait (?), cased photograph: 1 ambrotype, circa 1860 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Portraits of Lottie Allen and Lilian -----, cabinet photographs, circa 1903 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Unidentified family portraits (?), circa 1910-1920 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Portraits of Lula Allen and Robert Allen, reproductions (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Portraits of Harry Cardozo and Helen Cardozo (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Photograph album of Lula Allen (including photographs of Mattie and Myron McAdoo), 1916-1917 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Page from photograph album of Lula Allen (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Cabinet photograph of scene in Cape Town, South Africa, circa 1895 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Photograph album, exterior scenes (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Snapshots, circa 1930-1960 (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Scrapbooks, 1886-1895; Series II
  - Fisk Jubilee Singers Tour of Australia, 1886-1888 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - "McAdoo's Virginia Jubilee Singers and Concert Company, Clippings from Papers throughout Australasia" (with sheet music laid in), 1892-1895
- Personal and Family Papers, circa 1850-1966; Series III
  Arranged in rough chronological order. Financial papers relating to Mattie McAdoo are arranged as a group at the end of the series.
  - Family record, Allen Family, circa 1850-1875, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Program, Fisk Jubilee Singers, circa 1886 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Marriage certificate, Orpheus and Mattie McAdoo, 1891 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Wedding invitation, Orpheus and Mattie McAdoo, 1891 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Sheet music, circa 1892-1902 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Birth certificate and announcement for Myron McAdoo, 1893 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Agreement between Joseph G. Stevens and Orpheus McAdoo, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Clipping related to Orpheus McAdoo, 1896 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, Orpheus McAdoo: 1 postcard, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Presentation card to Orpheus McAdoo (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Orpheus McAdoo's will, exemplification of probate, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Clipping related to Mrs. Martha Allen, 1905 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Dinner menu signed by Mattie McAdoo and others, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Advertisement for performance of Mattie McAdoo, Robert Allen, and Lula Allen at Opera House, circa 1910 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Clippings and other material related to Mattie McAdoo, circa 1910-1930 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Diaries, Mattie McAdoo, 1915, 1933, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Material relating to Myron McAdoo, 1917-1918 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence, Mattie McAdoo, 1918-1933 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Clippings related to death of Mattie McAdoo, circa 1936 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Phyllis Wheatley YMCA, circa 1936 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Illustrated greeting cards and drawings by Ralph Vaughn (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Postcards received by Bertha and Lula Allen (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Blank postcards (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Material relating to Lula Allen (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Dorothy Porter's notes and research on McAdoo (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Address book (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Material relating to Myra McAdoo, circa 1966 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Financial papers relating to Mattie McAdoo
    - Account books, 1901-1933 (Box 5, Folder 51-52)
    - Bank book (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Money order, 1901 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Deed of trust, 1903 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Stock certificates, 1900-1948 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Warranty deeds, 1916-1917 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Returned checks, 1924-1936, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Estate settlement of Mattie McAdoo, check books, 1937-1944 (Box 5, Folder 59)
- Artifacts, circa 1895; Series IV
  - Beads and beaded jewelry, circa 1895; (13 items) (Box 6)
  - Spearhead; wooden pipe; wooden frame, circa 1895; (3 items) (Box 7)
  - Fans, circa 1895; (8 items) (Box 8–9)
- Oversize
  - "McAdoo's Virginia Jubilee Singers and Concert Company, Clippings from Papers throughout Australasia" (from Series II) (Box 10, Folder 60)